hello
it is march 9th 2022
we're here in actin flab guest stream
number 17.1 with mao abrasion and mao is
a product director at game addict
a researcher at versus computational
phenomenology lab and finishing a phd in
cognitive computing at uq am
we'll have a fun discussion today feel
free to write any questions in the chat
during the presentation and we'll
have a great time learning so thanks a
lot
for joining this guest stream and really
looking forward to what you have to
share
yeah thanks for having me i'm really
glad to be able to present this paper
we've uh we've submitted it and we're in
the process of reviewing it so it's a
really exciting paper that i'm hoping we
can get out
soon
so
today i'm going to try to go through a
lot of big concepts and how they apply
an active inference and then i'm going
to try to explain
um the nitty gritty of a generative
model how to make a simulation and then
what are the takeaways and limitations
i'm going to try to keep this quick if
you have any questions feel free to ask
them and i'll take anything as it goes
so
let's uh begin with the main concept
here which is uh confirmation bias and
conformity
this uh this was the the starting point
of our research
we were we were thinking with my
co-authors
which are connor hines
and daphne demacus and maxwell ramstead
we were trying to think through
what leads people to see the world in
such a way that they
have a hard time then reconciling their
view of the world with other people
and so it went back to the practice of
exchanging ideas sharing concepts and
values uh between different minds which
is a fundamental process
it really allows humans and
other living agents to coordinate and
basically operate socially
by sharing ideas uh individuals
communities
can really pursue their pragmatic goals
so basically um
you know get food is one of the
permanent goals you might want to
optimize for
um they improve their understanding of
the world
and then
we notice that humans are compulsory
co-operators
human individuals
and
survive based on the predication that
they have access and they can leverage
the bodies of accumulated cultural
knowledge
over the course of evolutionary history
humans have developed an
exquisitely sensitive capacity to
discriminate between reliable sources of
information from unreliable ones which
seems counterintuitive in the age that
we're at but you have to understand how
far we've come
before we got to the to the arms race
towards misinformation
so
the epistemic process as i just said
it's really not without flaws
humans are not
computing machines they're not perfect
they mostly use heuristics
they process information by reasoning to
limit the consumption of energy and
facilitate rapid decision making that's
that's the basis of
survival
for example confirmation bias
uh implies that all other things being
equal individuals who prefer sticking to
their own beliefs over changing their
minds it's
easier for them to potentially um
change their model less than if they had
to really all the time constantly deal
with the volatile model of the world
there's a lot of research about
confirmation bias and its relation to
cognitive dissonance we really don't
like cognitive dissonance we don't like
feeling like the world is not what we
understand it to be
and when we're faced with information
that conflicts with our core beliefs we
do in fact
experience cognitive dissonance
the tolerance for cognitive dissonance
tends to vary across individuals but
there's people who can really tolerate a
wildly volatile world and they accept
that they don't know things and they
said that they could be wrong and then
there's personality types who are
much less likely to take this dissonance
and and are more
likely to try to avoid this dissonance
and so confirmation bias in this way has
a social influence
individuals will prefer sampling data
from their in-group and will seek to
confirm their own ideas by foraging for
confirmatory information from their
in-group
this allows ensures that they have
access to like-minded allies
and they choose to belong to communities
where their deeply held beliefs are
promoted and shared this limits the
cognitive effort that is already
expended in the forging of information
this in-group delivery
um also influences how strongly
information is integrated so if a group
membership is important for the
individual
uh they'll tend to integrate
way more information that comes from
someone they believe believes the same
things as them
for instance you can think of news
sources and fox news so people it's not
like people from different aisles don't
know what the others are saying they
just tend to
take what their preferred channel says
and completely ignore what other
channels are saying even if they've
heard it
so
the confirmation bias is echoed by
another
uh heuristic and we're talking about
conformity so that's the need to cohere
with the beliefs of one's in groups so
it's kind of a
push and pull right i want to be
in a group of people who are like-minded
and i want to believe the same things
that i believe therefore going in a
group of people who are like-minded is
the best way to do so
i also don't want to be kicked out from
the group because the group has access
to a lot of resources that is very good
for me right
um
it limits how much information any one
agent has to gather to be part of a
group
uh it also increases how much each agent
is trusted
um
in-group agents can be way more
precisely predicted
by their their the other members of
their group
uh this is in part due by
norms and behaviors scripts we wrote
another paper about this
and generally these scripts tend to
benefit the members of the group right
um that's why they also want to uphold
these um these scripts
so being able to sample from the group
entails a continued relationship to
other members
if i lose access to this i can lose
access to information food shelter and
you know
it leads to difficulties
if you want to read more i can
eventually give you all the resources
so
this is a natural stopping point if you
want if you have any questions if you
have any notes you can share them now
it was really
powerful what you said about the losing
access
to the group benefits especially from
just the evolutionary and ecological
point of view
what are the scripts
and how does this current work that
you're sharing relate to the work that
you had done with narrative and scripts
yeah
so i mean the definition of scripts is
not
perfectly shared across the board
there's a lot of fields that use it but
the way that we've reviewed the
literature and brought together we have
weak scripts and strong scripts so we
weak scripts are like
clusters of connected uh concepts that
tend to exist with one another in a sort
of um
it's like it's like the building of a
context with naturally co-occurring
concepts and then the strong scripts is
how these concepts tend to
uh sequence over time so like for
instance um there is going to be a
natural entailment to certain events
that they gather the concepts together
and then you're going to be able to to
exist in a space like this
um
and that's that's how you
you norm not only how people behave in a
group but how they coordinate that is
how you norm how they uh sample reality
because let's let's imagine my script in
this place says that i must do this this
and that so i'm going to do this this
and that which means i'm not going to
have access to all the other things i
might have done if my script had been a
little different so that's one way that
we um we force people to only look at a
subset of the of the available
information in a given space
cool and then how did it
relate or how does this research build
upon what you had done
[Music]
those few months ago
right so the the previous paper had
formalized what a script means in terms
of active inference and basically
um
you with
you as an agent with your niche
um
predict
what you're um what you're supposed to
do next so it it it puts a strong
emphasis on your on on your available
policies and the way that your policies
are shaped and then
you're going to
tailor your prediction error on the
response of the nation so then you're
going to get to this sort of
um sequenced patterns of synchronization
that reinforce each other right so the
more
i get the right pattern the more i'm
likely to get good reinforcement and
therefore i'm going to you know
think that this is the right pattern for
this group and this is going to shape
the niche so much so that if anyone even
wants to or tries to enact something
different they may just get so much
prediction error that you know people
just
will will push back on it and you're
gonna stay within this sort of manifold
that has you know
the center points that that
gets all the states in but
the way that we're using this research
to build on the previous one is that
we understand that a script takes many
forms right the weak version of the
script is really
something you could call an ideology
right so if you take all of my weak
scripts
really what this is is
how do i map my observations to my
states it's really what it is right
and so this new research is saying well
agents are going to map things
differently
and thus they're going to end up into
different groups by simple virtue of
mapping
so differently that eventually it makes
no sense for them to try to interact
with one another because they couldn't
synchronize anyway so that's
um that's that's where that's how this
builds upon the previous research
cool does that make sense
yeah
please carry on
okay so we've discussed confirmation
bias and conformity and we've discussed
how they mutually reinforce each other
so to save energy confirmation bias
leads
to agents being drawn to groups that
validate their opinion and increase the
probability of behavioral and epistemic
conformity right believe the same things
and they form the basis of information
spread so agents spread information
through media and through connections to
one another given a network structure
right
um and the spread of ideas and behaviors
serves local
and larger scale coordination this is
very much based on the work of maxwell
who has effectively um discussed how
active inference
works across scale in nested
markov blankets that eventually build
and become one another
so
similar norms and coordination can be
understood as synchronization
which lowers the cost of information
flow
this increases the certainty of the
message being spread as well as the
quality of its reception so just right
there this increased certainty the
capacity to spread messages this uh
quality of reception you can see already
how this might lead towards better
synchronization right because um more
certainty means you may have less
attention to give to one thing
in order for it to happen and you can
start thinking about other things and
and start specializing in in other areas
with this certainty staying up right
uh the message will be more intelligible
to group members who share the common
set of codes uh and agents who are more
likely to integrate new information if
it fits better with their understanding
of the world
so
one example of optimization of message
passing includes hashtags
they have been known to be heavy
carriers of information in echo chambers
they they're used in partisan ways to
reach people of similar mindsets who
understand what the hashtag means and
understand that this is a signal for
them to interpret what's being said in
the life they want to interpret
so the spread of information is
optimized through hashtags as
pseudo-meta-linguistic categorization
markers that was those a lot of words
but really really what it means is just
that uh we see a hashtag
we know what it means we know it has a
lot of meaning without having to have a
whole text for it which is great for
twitter right
um
so
we labeled our communities in this study
um
formed in the process of belief sharing
as
epistemic communities now this term
already exists it was already used by
other um other fields but we've tailored
it a little bit to mean specifically
that our communities that share and
spread a worldview
or a paradigm or normalized sampling
behaviors
individuals in the community are tied
together by these practices which
reinforce the social signals acting as
evidence for the shared model of the
world so hashtags
the echo chamber formation is an extreme
example of epistemic communities echo
chambers type people with similar views
together and they tend to actively work
against the engagement with external
sources
they become very epistemically
vulnerable when members can really no
longer assess when an information is
true or not
only having access to a few sources
limits how much information can be
gathered and relevant sources of
evidence really fall through the gaps
and error will be propagated because it
goes really well really fast and is
integrated really strongly and so if the
people can no longer tell whether it's
false or not then the the
the system is much likely to to be more
vulnerable to misinformation and errors
they'll have a difficult time to check
errors against anything and um most
mines in the echo chambers will become
more and more synchronized and thus
poised to make the same mistakes
um so that's a pretty uh that's pretty
chunk right there
if you want we can like take a beat
yeah
i had a question
what does a healthy usage of hashtags
look like
or how do we
compress
information and context and perspective
in a way that might not have some of
these like threats or failures that
you're talking about
so for the first parts i
i have an idea but i've never read
anything that specifically said this is
a healthy you saw i'll venture a guess
but i'll start with the second part of
the question that will give you a good
sense the way to keep communities
healthy is to force them to be exposed
to viewpoints they may not agree with
sources that they're not um
necessarily familiar with
and that have
more
nuanced takes so the more you expose
people to
different kinds of people different
kinds of beliefs the more likely they
are to
depolarize and be more open to
possibilities
that's just a fact like we may think
through experience no you know what when
i see my uh
my conservative uncle
my racist homophobic conservative uncle
when he talks
my teeth grit and i stop listening
yes that's true
but you still are exposed to him
you still have to engage with his
thoughts to some degree and so your
reaction to push him away
that's a natural reaction and you know
you might actually do it but
if you're never ever exposed to his
thoughts you will never be able to
actually first of all really know
whether they're not true because you
you've never engaged with them right
so
that's one thing so the the guess about
the hashtags is
maybe try to
research hashtags that are not part of
your community
and try to reach people
who
may not normally listen to you in a
language that is potentially less
polarized
so if you really want someone the best
example of this is um
oh so she's a youtuber she's amazing
natalie
wynne do you know her
not familiar right now
uh i i just the thing is just i don't
remember the name of her channel but
uh
she basically specialized in
philosophically deconstructing
um conservative talking points in a way
that um
steel manned them
and didn't just destroy them on a sort
of
you know
value-based basis it was more like let's
take these points let's remove
everything that actually really isn't
true and take the kernel of truth in
there and understand it through their
eyes and reinterpret why this might
actually still be wrong but not in a way
that was demeaning and she reached a lot
of people this way she reached a lot of
conservatives who were like
wow okay no you know what i get it and
and it was very effective so
i think that's the answer to your
question
cool carry on
maybe
i'm sure we'll be able to bring active
inference in but it's awesome to be just
building the context and seeing how
there was motivation um and the
perspective on the work
awesome
so yeah so
one of the elements that
maybe will in fact give you a good sense
of how we're bringing active inferences
is the concept of volatility and habit
formation so
stability in the group is not guaranteed
optimal inference in a changing world
requires integrating sensory data right
with beliefs about the intrinsic
volatility of the environment
so
environments with higher quality
volatility change more often and thus
have shorter intrinsic time scales
at which the agent has to keep updating
their beliefs and conversely
environments with lower volatility
require you know longer time scale to
start updating your beliefs
um on the other hand
so um
having a better ability to track
potentially important fluctuations in
information requires to pay attention to
smaller changes but increased attention
to environmental fluctuations will
potentially lead to increased
sensitivity to random non-informative
changes in the environment so that might
be called a higher false positive rate
right so
it's important for agents to is to have
the right step um understanding of the
volatility in their environment
one way to cope with volatility is to
use the copic mechanism
to constrain the uncertainty related to
their own behaviors via habit formation
so
um here we're going to model habit as a
form of behavioral reinforcement where
behaviors become more probable as a
function of how often they are engaged
so an agent has engaged in a given
behavior enough a habit can then be
formed and become hard to unlearn and
this is important as we understand both
how parameters are set in our generative
model but also how echo chambers can
form by habit formation
so in our model behavior is driven by
information seeking
which drives uh it's a drive that leads
agent to preferentially sample
information from other agents with
beliefs that they believe are similar to
their own so this um
the way that i'm saying this believe
that they believe is important in active
inference because the inactive inference
we're starting from the assumption that
we don't ever really know things are
kind of hidden from us and we have to
infer what things might be so i never
really have access to what the other
person believes
i think
they might think this and i'm going to
try to infer their beliefs based on some
observations they're putting out into
the world
okay
now we've
point that down
let's start with
doing friends so we're getting to the
meat of it i'm gonna do a very uh short
introductory inference if you already
know great if you don't then this is
gonna be very informative
it's a biologically motivated framework
that rests on first principles of
self-organization in complex adaptive
systems
so
self-organization part is probably the
most important part here because active
inference is potentially less
interesting for rocks for instance
because they they tend to self-organize
a little less um i'm pretty sure we
could effectively use it for larger
models of um astrology but in uh sorry
astronomy but effectively what you
really care here is for things that tend
to fight entropy
so it's focused on the notion that
internal states of any biological system
are statistically insulated from the
environment that generates sensory
observations so basically they have an
inside and they have an outside
um
and so they engage in inference about
the the causes of what gives them
sensory states to really behave
optimally to keep fighting entropy
so biological systems entertain a
generative model of the latent
environmental causes of their sensory
input so latent because i don't know
really what causes it i can only infer
so it's a little different from
reinforcement learning or reflexive
behavioral algorithms um because actions
taken under active inference are guided
by these internal beliefs
and themselves they are optimized with
respect to an internal world model or a
representation of the world's causal and
data-generative structure we call the
generative model
agents in active inference represent
their own actions in their generative
model
by performing inference on both
hidden environment states of the world
and the consequences of their own
actions
they can select behavior which first
achieves their goal or fulfills
preferences
and second
reduces uncertainty in the age and world
model so this is where we get to the
epistemic part right i don't
i want a certain the world to be a
certain way
and i also want to be less uncertain
about
my uncertainty of the world being the
certain way right
so an agent's main objective is to
increase their model evidence
and to reduce suppress
surprised that like
a consider an agent which is in the
world um
if
i want to predict myself surviving i
want to see things which are likely to
make me survive
if i'm surprised by something it's
probably not likely to make me sir
survive and therefore it's probably
something i should avoid like for right
now i'm in my room i expect the room to
stay where it is as it is this is good
if we're there were to appear on my
right
would be very surprising and probably
very bad for me
so
processes like learning perception
planning and goal-directed behavior
emerge from this single drive to
increase evidence for the agent's
generative model of the world
so far
still good
so the agents never directly act on
sensory data but they change their
belief about what causes that data
this is a core step in active inference
it consists in optimizing these beliefs
using a generative model
it's also known as bayesian inference or
bayesian model inversion
this inference answers the question
what is my best guess about the state of
the world
given my sensory data and my prior
beliefs i don't come into the world not
knowing anything
i have some
basic beliefs about how what's what's
going to happen and then i'm getting
observations and i make predictions
about what might happen and then i act
on those predictions
this follows bayes rule
where the optimal belief about hidden or
latent variable
given some sensory data is called the
posterior distribution
um if you want
and keep going into that or i can skip
that automatically
but
but basically um
you you you basically calculate uh the
probability of something given something
else active inference perception
uh the generation of the best guess
about the current hidden states of the
world
is formalized as the computation of a
posterior distribution over some hidden
states
and action so the active part of active
inference
is the computation of a posterior
distribution over policies policies are
just a sequence of um of potential
states of the world
okay
so
now we introduce the actual model
is it is it clear so far is the active
inference part pretty clear
that's awesome you
hit on many great active
pieces
um
the only piece that really
i wanted to mention was the difference
between the observations like what was
said
and then the hidden
hypothesized cognitive states
it opens up a space between what
happened and why
somebody
said that
and
so that comes up all the time in
epistemic communities what did the
author mean by those words or what did
the person mean by saying that and so
that's why the context is so important
and active gives a framework that might
help us model that kind of a scenario
exactly and i mean this is this is
exactly where we're trying to go with
this research is that what right now we
want to model how
people tend to
have different views of the world but
the underlying phenomenon here and we're
going to try to dig more into that is
that
or the hypothesis anyway is that there
is a literal different mapping between
an observation
and a state which means for the same
thing being seen by two different people
we're going to infer two very different
things
and
the funny thing is
then you come into the world of values
where it's it's a whole other
scale and stuff
where
we may be interpreting the same thing
but we'll have a spin on it
and that spin being like
no no i know what he meant i just
fundamentally disagree with it and this
is how we get into the web these these
scripted webs of conceptual spaces where
um
you see these these graphs of concepts
being connected but at some point
there's a rift
and and that rift makes it so that i
value this and you do not and we're
still and so we can converge towards
understanding
without necessarily being able to
converge towards um acceptance
so this is still very hypothetical
though
one other note on on what you just said
there it's like the difference between
an orthodoxy and orthopraxis
so what is the similarity between
conformity of thought
and
latitude on action
vice versa
and then in what way are the
systems around us like aligned or not
with our preference about those features
of systems
yeah absolutely absolutely i mean i feel
like this could all be encased in c
right like we can interpret the same
thing but my fee is way over
there over here
so
i'll explain see later
this made very little sense a lot of
people
um
so let's introduce the model a little
more
um
we have individuals agents who share
information with one another and they
come to form beliefs about their local
environment and about the beliefs of
other agents in their community so to
understand this phenomenon we leverage
thus the active framework
here the organisms tend to
minimize a quantity called variational
free energy which quantifies the
divergence between the expected and the
sense data as explained before
from this point of view to select an
action is to infer what i must be doing
given what i believe and what i sense
so there's been a lot of work done in
this field on active inference to study
social systems i'm not going to go over
all of it but um there's really cool
studies i've just highlighted a few here
where basically um
systems uh minimize free energy give
rise to large-scale behavioral
coordination
much of the work though is still
theoretical so it'll be interesting to
see how experimental work can delve into
this um i know jonas mago
uh uh rudy pitia and maxwell ramsey are
doing a lot of work on this i think uh
lars senzvet as well as doing some cool
work on this
i'm just throwing on me
so um at first glance it might appear
difficult to model a phenomenon like
confirmation bias
using active inference formulation why
because
remember our agents are supposed to be
guided by the principle of maximizing
beijing surprise or earth silence which
requires to constantly seek out
information that is expected to
challenge one's world right because the
more surprised that consumed now the
less likely i am to be surprised later
right
but
information gain is subjective
um
epistemic value
or the the basin surprise or information
gain is always an expected surprise from
the point of view of the agent
it's in relation to the agent's set of
beliefs or genetic model
and because of this subjectivity
the informativeness of epistemic value
or or epistemic value of an action can
be
arbitrarily far from the agent's
expectation
so taking advantage of this
we gave agents what we refer to as
epistemic confirmation bias by building
a prior belief into the degenerative
model
that agents are more likely to sample
informative information from agents with
whom they agree a priori
and this a priori notion is important so
agents will sample agents with whom they
agree under the belief
that the agents are more likely to
provide higher quality information
there you go
um
this has a key difference with some
traditional opinion model so there's
been a lot of opinion models out there
not a lot with active inference but
definitely a lot with traditional
approaches
and so the implementation of bounded
confidence to motivate polarization is
usually hard-coded in the agent's
ability to perceive and thus update
their beliefs
in our model
polarization is motivated by the
positive effect of confirmation bias and
is thus directly
in the agent's model of the world
this allows agents to get more evidence
about their environment
if the information comes from another
agent that shares the same worldview
they're implicitly motivated in their
generative models
to gain more evidence about the world if
it confirms their pre-existing beliefs
also agents normally in traditional
models can directly perceive the belief
state of other agents right directly
perceived that's the key here
um
but in our model this is pretty we
believe this is unrealistic because we
we only infer the beliefs of others and
thus
um agents do not have direct access to
each other's belief states they they
infer the belief states and change them
through observation
um there's been a few recent
papers on that begin to build bayesian
models of opinion dynamics
which are motivated by the bayesian
brain hypothesis
a crucial point that distinguishes
approaches like active inference and
planning as inference from the genitive
bayesian approach is the notion that
actions themselves are inferred
behavior is cast as the result of
inference specifically by sampling
actions from a posterior distribution
over actions
so actions are selected in order to
achieve goals that minimize future
uncertainty and to maximize a lower
bound on bayesian model evidence
so um
we're using this to supplement the
goal-directed aspect of policy inference
which is driven by the expected free
energy
um and this becomes habits when the
prior over the actions becomes
inflexible right so if the prior over
action becomes so strong
it's just always going to be that right
um this prior is learned over time
and in the context of opinion dynamics
it can lead to a propensity to continue
sampling agents that have been sampled
previously so it's this idea of choosing
action through inference in accordance
with the minimization of uncertainty
it's a powerful modeling technique
because through the choice of policy
inference one can encode
various social behaviors like conformity
habit formation hostility and
indifference here we really only did um
habit formation because we had to focus
but eventually this could lead to very
very powerful
modeling tools for social uh
so
i can stop here before i launch into the
hypothesis
awesome with active inference let's keep
going
so we have three hypotheses
the first one is uh that we cast
confirmation bison actor inference as a
form of biased curiosity in which agents
selectively gather information from
other agents with whom they agree
um epistemic confirmation can mediate
the formation of echo chambers
uh and polarization in social networks
but we also believe that uh
confirmation bias episode confirmation
bias and network connectivity will will
mod and modulate the formation of
polarized epistemic communities
um hypothesis number two is we consider
the effect of agents beliefs about the
volatility of their social environments
so we try to see how beliefs about
social volatility impact their sampling
behaviors
and which itself may interact with
epistemic confirmation bias so we
hypothesize that beliefs about less
quickly changing social environments
will increase the likelihood of
polarization
and hypothesis tree
uh we hypothesize that we can model uh
selective exposure effects and
conformity through habit formation which
emerges through bayes optimal learning
so we show that agents will begin to
sample only those who belong to a
particular epistemic community
a greater learning rate for habit
formation will lead to clusters within
the network amplifying and quickening
the formation of echo chambers
so
the model
this is a multi-agent active inference
model
uh a group of agents
update their beliefs about an abstract
binary state that represents two
conflicting ideas and the opinion states
about these ideas
each agent also generates an action that
is observable
to other agents in the context of
digital social network we're using the
twitter linguistics but this was um we
basically tried to replicate
distributions that were fine in previous
studies on twitter
over time
each agent updates
posterior distribution or beliefs about
which idea is true
and as well as a belief about what a
connected set of other agents in the
network believes so basically what do
their neighbors believe
and uh both of these inferences are
achieved by observing the behavior of
other agents
agents can only observe the behavior of
one agent at a time so they have to they
have to um specific
pick who they want to uh look at
all right
the generator model
um i can go into detail if you want but
um this is pretty
i know it looks like a lot but it's
actually pretty simple
um these
encapsulate observations right so this
is the observation about uh what i'm
tweeting who i'm looking at and what
they're tweeting right
and then the a matrix
is mapping the probability of a state
having caused this observation so we
have states about like what is
um is the id true or not is it id1 is it
id2 um this is a bit blurry but uh
basically like uh which neighbor am i
looking at and
this one is who we're looking at what do
they believe right so it's it's it's
pretty simple mapping
here you have d which is the priors
um so what do i believe about the world
before having any observation about the
world then b is the transitions right so
how are the states likely to succeed one
another
here you have the the policies so uh
what kinds of actions am i likely to
take to bring about this uh this
exception of um
of of states
and c are my preferences
so then there are other terms but
they're a bit more complicated so i'm
not going to go into them but basically
these are the main um these are the main
things you have to know about a
generative model
so i'm going to skip real fast because
there were little arrows and i could
explain more but man
just yep
uh here
each agent's
each active reference agent in the
multi-agent simulation is equipped with
the same generative model
a single agent observes the action of
other agents
um they form beliefs about an abstract
binary environmental states and then
they choose actions which themselves are
observing observable to other actions
the focal agent consists of two
simultaneous choices
an expression and an observation so
basically what am i tweeting
and who am i looking at
an agent can only observe one neighbor
at a time so at each time step a vocal
agent both tweets its own hashtag and
chooses to read a hashtag tweeted by
another single agent so here we're
saying hashtag again this is just
linguistics right we could have said
anything basically these are numbers in
a matrix um effectively in a much more
complex model we could have had them um
read a hashtag and a sentence and then
try to infer what the sentence really
says like that we could have done
something much more complex but for now
the point was just to make them try to
infer a belief based on
hmm
i hope mal will rejoin and then we'll
continue
hey
are you there yep
so sorry i don't know what happened
oh we get all kinds of of surprises we
we prefer surprises here you can reshare
and just continue it was only a few
seconds but it was
it was great you know when you say the
right keywords
and then the internet short circuits it
happens
all right
well
i don't see you anymore oh yeah i'm here
no no i'm here
don't worry
i'll share my screen again
awesome actually can i no let's just go
with this okay can you see my screen
again and i'm back is everything cool
great great wonderful
we're back now where did you cut off
because i don't know if we kept talking
for a minute
um we heard observing one neighbor at a
time like and then how you could have
modeled more complex interaction effects
with uh like multiple artifacts yeah
right okay
awesome okay cool yeah
so
um now let's explain the hidden states
so what are the states they're trying to
infer
s idea so it's basically a binary
variable id one id two is id one true is
id two true
meta belief which is um
the particular neighbors beliefs about
which of the id is true so does my
neighbor believe this or not that
the tweet so
what am i tweeting
and who should i attend to which
neighbor am i attending to so um this
was actually very complex uh
daphne and connor did an amazing job
here because
we wanted to change the number of
neighbors and so the the matrices had to
grow in relation to how many neighbors
there were and they did it was it was
beautiful
the way that they did this so shout out
to connor who's obviously a genius and
daphne as well
um so
i'll discuss control sticks so control
states are
which of the states can my agents
actually act upon
so here it was um the tweet so i can
decide to tweet you know hashtag one or
hashtag two and i can decide to look at
neighbor
you know one through k
now
observation modalities what can they see
they can see their own tweets and this
is important because the thing is
oftentimes you have to have a sort of
identity mapping between your
observations and your states so that the
states can be taken into consideration
in the actions um so here you have to
know
what you're tweeting you have to know
what your neighbor is tweeting
and you have to know who you're
attending to right pretty simple
now for likelihood so
um you know in a palm dp in a generative
model we have to describe the
likelihoods that determine how hidden
states relate to observations right
um
so the entire a array is a set of
tensors with one sub-tensor per
observation modality each
modality-specific likelihood tensor is a
potentially multi-dimensional array that
encodes the conditional dependencies
between each combination of hidden
states and observations for that
modality
so we also have a transition model so
the transition likelihood uh the
dynamical likelihood uh in b that i
explained earlier the environmental
dynamics so um how are things likely to
change a higher value means the same
idea remains valid over time a lower
value means the same idea is less likely
to be true over time so more
environmental volatility and then um the
dynamics of
whether my neighbors are likely to
change their ideas of the world
then
the next component here is
the degenerative models the priors over
the observations
so in discrete
in discrete active inference we
represented these as vector c d and e so
um goal directed action is motivated by
appealing to a baseline prior
um over observations so that specifies
the agent's preferences so that's the c
i was talking about earlier what do i
want to encounter in the world what are
the outcomes i'd like to see and those
usually act as kinds of rewards
then there's the prime over hidden
states at the initial time step which is
the d vector it encodes the agent's
beliefs about the initial state of the
world before having made any
observations and um in the current model
we make the prior over control states an
empirical prior
parameterized by the link function
denoted by the et vector so i'm not
going to go too much into this but
basically this implies that the prior
over those control states corresponding
to tweet actions depending on the
posterior of the idea so basically your
agents are always going to tweet exactly
the same as they believed they're not
lying but they could but we could change
that
so habit learning under active inference
uh learning also emerges as a form of
variational inference so um it's not an
inference uh over hidden states but
rather over model
parameters
so the parameter inference is referred
to as learning because it is often
assumed to occur on a fundamentally way
slower time scale than hidden state and
policy inference
in this model we use habit learning to
model the development of epistemic
habits so as i said the the the tendency
to resample the same people
and so
um they simultaneously infer which
neighbor to attend to based on the
prerogative to minimize expected free
energy
and they also continuously learn the
habit based on the frequency with which
they tend to ask our neighbor
all right the actual simulation so
in a given simulation we had
several agents but we didn't always use
the same number of agents we were very
limited by computational constraints we
would have wanted to make something much
larger much bigger to really model an
actual social media but this is very
computational heavy in the future
studies we may try to increase the
number of agents but for now we tried to
stay between 12 and 30 agents
again same model for each agent at each
time step agents simultaneously update
their belief
and take an action each agent's
observation or a function of its own
actions at the previous time step as
well as the actions of a selected
set of neighbors at the previous time
set so not everyone is connected to
everyone so i don't need to see everyone
all the time
each agent has a fixed set of neighbors
where the particular neighbors are
determined by a randomly chosen network
topology
okay
all right so
so focal agents with a higher ecb
believes that tweets are more reliable
if they come from neighboring agents
that believe to share the same opinion
right to like-minded people
uh the inverse social volatility is a
parameterized focal agent's beliefs
about the stochasticity of the social
dynamics the learning rate is associated
with updating the habit vector over
neighbor attendance and network
connectivity um
is the number the way that individuals
um
[Music]
are connected to one another it's pretty
simple so these are the parameters that
we tweaked uh during the
during the simulations um you'll see
that um they tend to enter in interact
with one another and they're related to
the hypotheses we formed initially
so
this figure
um
is really cool
it visualizes opinion formation in a
single active inference agent and shed
light on the relationship between
inverse volatility and epistemic
confirmation
um
we use a simplified three agent setup
here so we just were trying to test
something at each time step the focal
agent chooses to read a hashtag from one
of its two neighbors and the two
neighbors are not actually
active inference agents here they're
just uh they're just part of the
generative process they're sources of
sequence of distinct hashtags and who
tweet hashtag one or hashtag two
and as you can see
a higher epistemic confirmation bias
induces a positive feedback effect where
the focal agent comes to agree with one
of its two neighbors with a higher
certainty
as you know it
it tweets the thing that it believes
um
even if it's exposed to a sequence of
hashtag over 100 time steps
the agent receives the observation and
um
here below each subplot the heat map
shows that the temporal evolution of the
probability of sampling uh neighbor one
versus neighbor two over time shows that
it's clearly it clearly goes towards the
one he started at prior with
um
the
beliefs in more metabolic volatility
lead to higher posteriors uncertainty
about the idea but it still eventually
leads to um
you know
believing in the same idea you initially
started
so
okay
now
this is much much more informative as to
the actual uh phenomenon and you can see
here that we have two very interesting
phenomenon
consensus and polarization
um
they emerge when simulating uh the
network
we can see that every agent is generated
by the action uh
the observations of every agent is
generated by the actions of other agents
um and so collective belief dynamics
here
under different generative
parameterization
really show um
the the evolving beliefs of all agents
about idea one or about idea two
in panel a and d we see polarization
where two subset of agents end up
believing in two different levels of the
idea of the idea hidden states with a
high certainty so you can really see
like they go very far it goes
one or zero it's not it's not like
0.6 no it's really one or zero they're
really certain
and panels b and c on the other hand
shows consensus where the whole network
converges on the same opinion by the end
of the simulation
this really showcases the rich
phenomenology uh displayed by
collectives of active inference agents
which validates our model really
alongside known opinion dynamics model
and that was really able to replicate um
distributions that we were trying to uh
to converge doors
do you have any questions
yeah um maybe go back to the slides
what kind of dynamics might result in
persistent diversity
or not just the absolute consensus or
absolute bifurcation but like you did
mention you said you didn't see
there to be a continuum of like people
who aren't sure
so what kind of parameters or what kind
of cognitive mechanisms
would facilitate that
so um lower epistemic confirmation bias
for sure
would would potentially lead to more
variety
we would look it to network structure
eventually uh lower habit formation
would definitely help as well as you can
see here it's uh
and and also higher belief in volatility
so if you believe that volatility is
high you're going to keep sampling a lot
of people because you do believe that
uncertainty is going to continue arising
right so these are three parameters that
really lead to more diverse and less
polarized beliefs and some ideas
because it's so interesting how you you
captured like the two things you can do
on
a classic social media platform which is
decide who to follow and then kind of at
a finer scale who to pay attention to
even though it's also partially like put
in front of you with a feed in the
algorithm but also it's a little bit of
agency in like what you pay attention to
and who you follow at a slower time
scale and then how you act
and how that modifies the epistemic
niche and some people follow a lot and
act little and vice versa and different
people's cognitive models get updated in
a different way
despite having access to similar
platform affordances
so these are really great points in
future studies one you might want to see
how the niche responds so right now that
they're they're crafting their niches
simply as a function of who they're
talking to right but you could also
model the algorithm
screwing with you right so the algorithm
knows you're looking for this so it's
going to cut some things from you
and so you you like for instance um one
way we could have done this is the niche
could have determined well okay well
you're listening less to this so
i'm not going to cut that connection i'm
just not going to let it be broadcasted
to you right now
so that's one way that the algorithm
works right it basically selects things
it puts in your feed even though the
people aren't gone they're still there
you just see them less so that's that's
one way we could have done like a
relationship with the niche and as you
said yeah we could have modeled
different kinds of behaviors for people
who are more lurkers right how do their
beliefs change if they're not showing so
that's one way that eventually we're
going to be able to model like
influencers
if they're people who potentially
broadcast to a lot of people and a lot
of the other people don't broadcast as
much so the beliefs of these people are
going to be super influential as opposed
to the beliefs of these smaller people
who are much less influenced so that's i
mean there's a lot that can be done it's
really cool uh but yeah
i'm excited about this the only problem
in life is there's not enough time but
yeah it's really cool
so anyway i'm gonna i'm
gonna keep going because we're going
towards the um
the cool plot
um so
there was an interaction between episode
confirmation bias and network
connectivity
here you can see a heat map of the
mean polarization index across like
independent realizations of the
multi-agent opinion dynamic simulations
for unique combinations of network
connectivity and epistemic confirmation
bias so in the bottom
the selected plot lines show extreme
settings of p
so
p02 and p08
and uh
y which is uh
yeah so shaded areas around each line
represent the standard deviation of the
polarization
index across independent realizations so
this is hypothesis one
we investigated hypothesis one or how
episomic confirmation bias so why and
network connectivity p determine
collective formation of epistemic
communities we systematically vary both
epistemic conformation bias so 15 values
for epistemic confirmation bias tilling
the range three and nine and network
connectivity so 15 values for p tilling
the range 0.2 to 0.8
in networks of 15 agents and over 100
different realizations of each
conditions for a hundred times steps so
it's really a lot it's really a lot but
the results are beautiful
and so we were trying to see how higher
epistemic confirmation bites in sparse
network might drive the emergence of
epistemic community uh through the the
formation of belief clusters that are
both dense and far apart in belief space
right so they really believe different
things
um to assess the emergence of epistemic
communities or clusters we define the
polarization index which measures the
degree of epistemic spread in a system
and so a high value of p so close to one
indicates more spread out beliefs and
implies clustering in echo chamber
formation whereas a low p
implies the network agents have similar
beliefs about an idea or you know less
um
less diversity or less polarization so
it shows the effects of varying
epistemic confirmation bias and network
connectivity on polarization
it is clear in the first column of the
heat map that highly spread out beliefs
can offer it can occur at all values of
epistemic confirmation bias in the
presence of a sparse connectivity
denser networks in general uh reduce the
risk of polarization
as seen by the by the drop-off
so
how increased episodic confirmation bias
can still counteract this effect to some
extent by marginally bumping up the risk
of polarization so this is a really
interesting result but it comes back to
what we were saying earlier a dense
network means there's a lot of people
who you can see the opinion of and who
may not agree with you so you have more
access to people's beliefs
sparser networks means you're very
quickly going to fall into an echo
chambers because you're going to cut off
some some people you don't want to
listen to and then boom
you have no more connection with these
people
there we go
so in this one um you see another heat
map
so these are really noisy we're sorry
about that uh we redid them
for the for the reviewers but they're
not ready
so
they're pretty noisy but i'm going to
help you uh make a little sense of them
so here you have a heat map of the
polarization index for 225 combinations
of inverse believe volatility so that's
hypothesis two
and epistemic confirmation bias
precision so the above right
heat map i don't know if i'm pointing to
the right i
yeah
the heat map of the re-attendance rate
for 225 combinations of inverse believe
volatility and epistemic confirmation
bias and below left it's a line plot of
the most extreme rows of the
polarization heat map so
below right is the plot line of the most
extreme columns of the reattendance heat
map
so for hypothesis two we modeled
behavior under different values of
inverse social volatility
to see how it would interact with
epistemic confirmation bias
we swept over epistemic
conformation bias and social volatility
and we measured the reattendance rate
and polarization index for each
configuration
it portrays a complex picture of the
relationship between ecb and inverse
social volatility
in the case of high volatility over meta
beliefs
agents are driven to periodically
re-attend to neighbors in order to
resolve growing uncertainty about their
beliefs
you can see a higher average
re-attendance rate
interestingly
there seems to be an interaction between
re-attendance rate and epistemic
confirmation bias such that in the
presence of both high volatility and low
epistemic confirmation bias the
reattendance rate is maximized so
they'll
they'll reattend the same people even if
they have low epistemic confirmation
bias
because you know
there is they oh sorry
they have high volatility they
constantly think that people are likely
to change their mind so they're going to
continue to keep attending these people
with um
a little bit of a lower of all
volatility they're it's not the lowest
though because if if you have the lowest
setting of volatility you're just you
know not
going to care so much what other people
think you're just gonna keep reattending
so we speculate that the absence of ecb
makes the epidemic value of attending to
every neighbor pretty much equally high
and thus agents are going to continue
revisiting neighbors uh sequentially
with the attendance preference for any
given neighbor solely dependent on the
time lapse between the last reading of
their last hashtag
um
so
this is interesting it will lead to
diverse social attendance patterns such
that agents will prefer to constantly
sample either new neighbors with no
particular neighbor left or uh
uncertainty driven resampling so they
can either
sample everyone for example the same
people but they but they'll they'll try
to attend to their neighbors a lot
okay so here we have
uh the last hypothesis hypothesis tree
we got there
it's a heat map of the polarization
index for all 225 combinations of
learning rate and epistemic confirmation
bias precision
so above right you have a heat map of
the re-attendance rate for 225
combinations
and epistemic confirmation bias so the
parameters represent the centers of the
normal distribution sampled from across
trials for each configuration
below left the most extreme row of the
polarization index heat map and below
right the most extreme column of the
reattendency map
so here we're trying to see if the
polarization of networks via habit
formation
follows hypothesis three
we swept over ecb so 15 values uh tiling
the range three to nine and learning
rates
so 15 values
tilling from zero to nine
and the networks were pretty small 15
agents with a connection probability of
0.4
and an inverse social volatility of uh
you know six
and as before the the same idea so nine
so
etb was again normally distributed with
a fixed mean
uh and a variance of one so we we we um
we sampled from a normal distribution
and we
eventually we lowered uh the the
variance and it it gave us much better
results but
um
the learning rate was fixed for the
condition to really understand what the
effect of it was
the learning rate incentivizes agents to
to the same neighbor by forming a habit
this competes with the epistemic value
of attending to a new neighbor with
unknown beliefs this tested the
hypothesis that a higher learning rate
stronger habit formation increased
polarization and here we can demonstrate
that a higher learning rate and
epistemic confirmation bias interact to
influence outcomes at the collective
level so a higher learning rate induces
more polarization implying the formation
of more stubborn epistemic communities
in the network
okay
so
do you want me to go into the takeaways
that'd be awesome
okay
so um
here
we showed a confirmation bias as an
epidemic phenomenon our agents have wise
beliefs
um
we
saw that ecb confers a higher weight to
information that comes from peers and
that can lead to a bad bootstrap
um
we find that opinion dynamics heavily
depend on network density this was not
counter-intuitive but the way that it
happens was a little bit
counter-intuitive
uh the clustering phenomenon is
exacerbated by adding the capacity to
form habits so this is important
we found that east tb
the presence of rabbit formation
exacerbated polarization due to the
formation of echo chambers or tight
communities of agents that only read
each other's hashtag
and
the contributing influence of beliefs
about social volatility to exploratory
social sampling
leads us to consider the role of norms
and social settings
if an agent is incentivized via
epistemic value or curiosity to pay
attention to neighbors whom they are
uncertain about their social group could
be a source of constant surprise as long
as their beliefs about the neighbors are
constantly fickle so in other words
even in the presence of a group of
like-minded peers
thank you
good burritos i guess um
burritos modification uh the best kind
of niche modification i know right
ghost brings me peruse um
so we we expect that increased beliefs
about social volatility leads to
repeated retentive peers amongst one
another
um
okay we have limitations in this work as
i said a very low number of people
uh we only modeled beliefs of two
believe two exclusive ideas it would
have been maybe more interesting to have
more and we would have wanted to um
to notice the emergence of similar but
distant sub communities as well um even
if they're not already uh connected
so yeah that was that was all of it that
was all of it
cool work
really
fun to hear about
um
nice
well if anyone's
watching live they can uh ask any
questions
otherwise what would you like to start
off by talking like when you present
that for what audience what do people
often ask about
um they ask the same questions you ask
really they ask um what can we do about
social media how do we factor in the
algorithm
uh what this can
how this ties into misinformation
um i guess this question we haven't
really talked about the notion of
misinformation
so that's something you're interested in
let's hear about it
yeah
so
this is this information is kind of a
tricky question right because you'd
think um
you'd think that misinformation would be
if it doesn't agree with us if it's
about something we don't agree with
we cast it instantly as misinformation
and in fact
um
we tend to fall very heavily for most
sources of misinformation the only thing
is
uh
we fall for misinformation that tends to
reinforce our view of the world so
even if it's part of a sort of
conservative
if you're if you're um
more liberal more um
i forgot the word for not conservative
but if you're more left
um if you're seeing some piece that's
been crafted by the right but it kind of
confirms your view of the world you're
more likely to integrate it
and this is this is pretty important
especially when we're trying to think
about
the q and on people and and
[Music]
people whose views aren't necessarily
completely polarized but who want to
view the world as something they
um
they can unfold right something they
have
they have control over the epistemic
value that they can gather
um
and so
they're being fed information which
feeds into that sort of meta view of the
world that they
they can understand the hidden truth
about the world and so
this becomes a sort of pool
you know where it doesn't really matter
when i pitch at you
so long as it gives you this sort of
sensation that you have access to
something that others really don't and
therefore you now understand the
structure of the world a little better
even if
when you take the whole thing together
when you look at the entire structure
of um
you know conspiracy beliefs
they're extremely unlikely extremely
complex
and one way that we've noticed that we
can um
identify these conspiracy theories
compared to you know
true facts they tend to have a really
interesting structure which is
they're very sparsely connected to very
large elements but like
normally in a true in a true story and
something that's real even if there's a
lot of elements or or fields that are
combined there's a lot of connections
amongst things right because because
it's real so you can really you can see
from a lot of directions these real
connections if you lose one connection
everything doesn't fall apart
in conspiracy beliefs
those connections are so sparse that if
you lose one the entire theory doesn't
make sense anymore
so
it's it's that's that's the kind of
structure that we see
so it's kind of sort of
you can see how this would have
epistemic value right because everything
is so surprising and uncertain that
people
would like feel a lot of value from
accruing all this information right so
i think that's where we fall into the
bad bootstrap but there are other kinds
of bad bootstraps like
um
let's say um
so i don't want to i don't want to make
any community feel like they're
being targeted or that
or or that i'm being negative towards it
but
there are communities like let's talk
about a cult right let's think about it
called who who starts believing a very
niche set of beliefs
and they the way that they do this is by
cutting off contact to everybody else
right so it's much easier for me to
instill a belief in you there's nobody
else to tell you this is this crazy this
like what are you doing
so one of the first thing is they tell
you to cut off contact with a lot of
people
they reinforce the beliefs constantly
they punish anyone who who dissents
because that's how you reinforce a
belief
and then you find them in these sort of
communities which are like
very only locally functional
and if you take someone out of that
community afterwards and you put them
somewhere else they're like
kind of lost because
well
that's not how the world works so like
they they they're they need to re-learn
a lot of things they need to um
develop behaviors that are distinct from
their previous belief systems that allow
them to exist and and you know be humans
in a already pretty complex civilization
system
that was very interesting about the
resilience of the meta view so
how do we
use active inference to
study these different phenomena like how
do you connect the nodes and edges from
the graph the generative model the
cognitive model
how does that
visualization representation connect
with like the phenomena that we want to
model
i mean that's the
that's the question isn't it that's what
we're working on at the computational
phenomenology lab
i have a theory um but it's not like
it's still being developed but my sense
is
um
you're gonna start treating
events as observations right and you're
gonna start treating
so you're a node you're here in the
graph
and everything around you is a sort of
observation
and you're you're trying to determine
layers in the graph which becomes states
right so you're going to move across the
graph by trying to predict uh
effectively what is the next state and
trying to see if this new thing that
you're going to observe matches with the
state you're trying to see so um
so that's just how you move in the graph
and then
the way that you're going to establish
what is
true or not so that's one way to do it
there are other ways right there's also
swarm um beliefs and stuff but like
one way to do it is well
how much can i predict from this node
how much is actually connected to this
node and if if we take this structure
again of like the
the graphs which are sparsely connected
and don't allow for any connection to be
lost
you're going to start seeing that
there's going to be a lot of dense
connections between concepts
and it's going to be very easy for you
to sort of find your way through the
graph and be like well i can go there
and i can go there and i can go there
and and and try to make
predictions about the next potential
nodes given these two that you or these
three that you already have right i have
these three things and i know
everything's sparse it's densely
connected i can go there it's easy and
and if i go there i don't lose any
connection to anything else so that's
one way another way to do this is
agents are going to start forming
beliefs by observing real life or
reality
and agents who
have a lot of observations about the
world
are likely to you know have a more
accurate model of the world so the more
they make predictions about things that
eventually happen the more we can give
them a reliability rating right so like
this person
sees a lot of things one and two when
they say something it tends to happen so
we give them a high rating
and then you know the agents talk to one
another and sort of like uh coordinate
their beliefs and eventually there's
gonna be this dude over there that you
know says green and everybody else says
right it says red and it's like well you
know
the probability of this green being true
like there's a high surprisal there
the kicker is
there's a high surprise though so we're
giving it a lower reliability rating but
if it does end up happening well then
the value is
you know it is much higher as well right
because we reduced a lot of variational
free energy here so like
like i think that's that's how we're
going to get to these two things
combined with the the graph
leading to the nodes that you can
connect together and
the agents with reliability ratings that
swarm towards a true belief are ways
that we can integrate these things i
think
cool the first mode you had i kind of
wrote down it was like dense connections
ideas that have grounding you know good
maps for territories
more stable territory
more effective map
it's like in a family if you went to
someone else's family reunion you
shouldn't be too surprised that any
given two people know each other
because there's kind of a coherence or
there's a prior about the density of
that network whereas if the network's
very sparse
then
um
the coherence of it is susceptible to
single facts being wrong so you kind of
point it to like where a thread will be
tied well this person knew that person
that this money was sent here and then
it's like if even one of those things
weren't true then the whole contraption
is fallacious
um
and then and then like the dense
connections
have an element of conformity to them
because you have an intrinsically
validating world model like the
epistemic network of epicycles
and that way of predicting how the
planets moved and then you have
insight from outside that goes against
the conformity bias the prior
but that can be how the community can
move into a new
space
so we can't have like just novelty
driven like simply different is better
but we can't have simply the same is
better
puts us in this active inference
situation which is why it's so cool to
see
epistemic modeling like you have all
done
there's something really interesting
here about
the optimal space um
around which
you start
you know
computing the right amount of
information so
mark miller is working on this alex
kiefer is working on this as well um i
know that we're working on it with also
alejandra syria bruno lara so there's
this whole group we're working on like
what is the optimal computation space
right um
and so
this is this is truly the question you
just posed should i stay exactly where i
am or should i try consuming error and i
think that's the beauty of groups and
this is where we sort of fall into what
what a group is in terms of a market
blanket right
so
in the inner spaces of a group you'll
have people who are less likely to start
consuming error
they're just like you know they're just
staying within what's being done and and
and that's stability right and then
towards the external parts of the group
there are people who are more
connected to other groups right and then
who can start consuming error and this
because the internal parts of the group
are very densely connected to one
another because you know they're an
in-group
this error can be passed in like um it
can be consumed in a way that is
efficient for the group to deal with
through this like sort of um
blanket
so the the real question becomes like
what's an active state what's a sensory
like
yeah a state at the level of a blanket
for a group but you can start you can
start to conceptualize it as like
you know your influencers and your
lurkers right like the lurker is
consuming information and the
influencers promote information and then
this whole thing becomes sort of like
there are people who
just consume what this one do says and
there are people who just like
um
push out information and then maybe they
take a little bit of information but
they have like you know this
this sparse network of people who are
like like you know people who are like
90 000 followers but they themselves
follow three
so
so so then there's this like sort of
layering of people who listen to others
and so the the smaller people who have
less followers they're still connected
to one another and there's degrees of
through which um i think information is
passed and consumed and so
what mark miller is trying to say is
that
the computational optimal is where
you compute enough error
that you continue to
uh
to grow in your sort of fitness
landscape so you're still learning about
things you're still
discovering
but you're still stable enough that no
error is going to topple you right
so because you have all these other
people here
who keep your group relatively stable
you know that consuming a little bit
isn't gonna like destroy your group
right it's like
it's like think of um of a polycule like
we're we know we're in love this new
metamorph is not gonna like
break our up
so it's good right um
so
that's that's i think what allows like
this sort of large-scale coordination
among groups is that there are people
who are like specialized in consuming
the error and who can only do this
because there are other people who
ensure there's resources being produced
for them
yeah
well um two thoughts so
one the core to periphery or fringe
continuum it also happens like in ant
colonies where there might be a brood
chamber
that is the most homeostatically
controlled and then there's like a
periphery out to like kind of a lobby or
an anti-chamber where there is a lot
more like in and out and then of course
that's the interface like with the
external world
and so then there's um analyses with
tracking of like where the ants go
and so there'll be some who's continue
whose distribution spatially is more
like the top parts of the nest or just
the entry room and a little bit in and
there might be another one that spends
more of its time
towards the core and spends then it goes
a little bit out um
but that last piece you said like
what roles
contribute to colony or epistemic
community
stability or collective open-mindedness
or resilience like those are such
critical questions that people frame
qualitatively
every day
and so
it's just really cool to
have the conversation
and open it up to many different
perspectives about what roles do play in
communities and then
try to
use the model
to follow up and
describe
complex situations rather than like
constraining to what
communities can be or how they can
regulate
yeah
and there's something beautiful about
active inference here right because we
could like we can literally potentially
measure or predict
what might be an optimal state for a
group given the free energy that the
group can consume right so if we can
understand how this consumption of error
can be distributed over the group or at
least can be absorbed um we can say well
listen
we don't need to destroy your your q
anon group all we need to do is
give you a little bit
you know like enough in the right
distributed areas so that you guys
integrated on your own and potentially
shift without us having to
uh further push and and potentially even
polarized like one of the worst things
you can do with one of your q and on
family members is antagonize them
because then they isolate and they're
gone you're never finding them again
like they will they will be lost to that
thing which will consume them
and this is and it's it's not just true
for for
for fringe groups it's it's true for a
lot of groups where we're like
we rely on that community for survival
as we said like there's a lot of
communities out there who need to stay
tight-knit because well it's beneficial
for them to be tight-knit
so um
let's say we're like a city right and
and there's nothing wrong inherently
about being a city and what you want to
do is to try to prevent a catastrophe
right
but we can't
we can't all be researching
the types of catastrophes that might
happen and like someone's gotta you know
make bread
right so so you start having these
people who
you can predict over time that i don't
have to think about this i don't have to
pay attention to this scale
because i'm paying attention to this and
i know that
they can rely on that so my model of the
scales makes it so that my role is super
clear
and allows for others to make these
predictions right so
i think i mean it's not fully um it's
not fully realized yet and there's a lot
of work
to be done still but i feel like we you
know we have it's right there it's right
there
here's something that kind of makes me
think about like the city
is enabled by specialization and all
these other features
um
what are
epistemic infrastructure projects
like what are the
thankless or
thankful jobs
that people do like moderation
governance
care for themselves and for other
participants like what are those
infrastructure tier
roles where it's like this is building
the road
so we we have to contextualize how well
this shop does in light of
the effort to build the road and the
community that contributed there and so
it kind of like opens up the idea of
attribution
and community and it's like very
generative space
yes i feel like they um
it would be
would be difficult to say that there is
a very clear distinction in any given
infrastructure right so like
every field
has
people who innovate every field has
people who just stay on tradition every
field has people who just provide like
it's not it's not just like bakers just
provide right there are people who
innovate in bread there are people who
think of new recipes or think of new
ways or try to bring the same recipes to
different parts of the world so like
it's it's more distributed than that
but
um i i really
i really do think that these structures
kind of self-emerge
right so like
we all kind of have not i'm not gonna
make that
but i do believe that there's um a
natural instinct to
um to try something new
once you have
the certainty
that isn't gonna fall under you
right
and because we have this sort of
distribution of like uh people who have
more or less money and people who have
had past experiences of having more or
less money
they kind of tend to focus and so it
naturally sort of synchronizes into well
you know what i was poor my whole life
i'm gonna be careful i'm not gonna go
crazy and that's why you know that the
fallacy of the entrepreneur who had like
nothing and he became something like
that that is bull like it is so easy to
be an entrepreneur when you have barely
anything to lose you know the notion of
risk
and capitalism
isn't true
you
they can do it because to them the risk
is minimal if i lose everything tomorrow
i can do it again
so there isn't really a risk whereas if
if little lady over there who has like
20 000 in her bank account decides to
put everything in a business is a real
risk it's a real risk and
like
obviously she's less likely to do it
because like
what happens to her children if she
loses everything you know i mean like so
there's going to naturally be these
tears of people who because of the the
their states faced right so the
probability of them continuing accessing
resources over time is is less
spread out
they they have to stay con concentrate
on this and by virtue of doing this they
also you know keep producing um
value and resources for people who
tend to accrue this
and thus have more way to you know trash
it out and innovate i mean
there's a reason that it's so easy to go
to university when your parents are rich
like obviously if you if you parents
have the means to support you you're
going to try and continue studying
longer and longer and it's much harder
if you have to support yourself it's not
impossible but it's so much harder so
anyway
yeah capitalism
well
to connect it to active inference you
kind of brought up the situational
risk sensitivity and how that relates to
someone's experience and their situation
and then
in
active inference the policy selection
for whether the binary decision
go to this
university or go to
some other path or a continuous policy
it's broken down into that pragmatic or
kind of outcome or goal reward
orientation as well as the epistemic
and so
what happens when people
don't have to
have anxiety or find out epistemically
about how they're going to get pragmatic
reward for their action
and
how does that
move us beyond the sort of like
web 2 engagement maximization
[Music]
relationship with platforms where
there's a very specific generative model
generative process relationship
and it's based around like behavioral
summaries of the person's time spent on
the site or like their spending or
something like that versus like taking
the cognitive rains
and saying we want to have
lower anxiety and we want people to be
exposed to different perspectives or
some other
preference for platforms that's
specified using an active inference
framework
there's a lot in there
ah
so i'm going to try to
so think of a think of
the generative model always like
generative models aren't
one scale right there's scales on scales
on scales and scales on scales and what
happens when you when you go across
scales is that your your state's at one
level becomes the observation at the
next level and then it embeds and embeds
it in beds
okay and then
the embeddings can sort of like again
track into one another so i'm here and
um
there's the bear so i'm gonna stop
focusing on you which is a higher level
i'm gonna focus on directly this right
now and there's the bear and i'm gonna
focus on the bear but eventually the
bear goes away because then you know i
was having a hallucination and
suddenly i can go back to a higher level
and start monitoring other things and
notice okay well you know what this
lasted a long time and maybe i should be
cooking because i'm gonna get hungry so
i'm gonna you know slowly navigate the
scales of where where i'm supposed to
put attention based on how the free
energy is is rising at a given point in
this form
all this is to say
um
for the web or for monitoring
or for resource attribution
what am i really trying to do what i'm
trying to do is to make sure that a
person
never has to feel like they're
constantly putting out fires
so anxiety is that right anxiety is the
constant belief that you're like peaking
everywhere and you have to pay attention
to everything you're hyper sensitive so
let's let's lower that let's feel like
you can start like giving a little bit
more attention to a longer time frame or
even a shorter one but just on the
moment
because like all of the parts of your
model are pretty certain like there's
not going to be a fire
so like
i have certainty across all my scales
and i'm going to start paying attention
to just this now and then like
i don't need to like you know give too
much to my model
how do you do this with monitoring well
with monitoring you're like well look
given this trajectory right now and
given this personality type and given
like what we know already about her
she's gonna freak out in about five
minutes about x and i'm monitoring this
so before she freaks out let's
give a little reminder about this or
like um
actually through iot or whatever let's
start something like my dream is like
in the morning i wake up my breakfast is
like started like nobody's starting it
for me it's just starting so
you know i do my my house
predicts the kinds of things i'm likely
to need so that eventually i i never
like
ever have to feel like i need to pay
attention to anything with too much like
which too much uncertainty is going to
rise anymore i'm not sure i answered
your question exactly but i feel like
i'm going in that direction
there's the um
preparing your breakfast when you wake
up and there's sort of the
cybernetics 1.0 version which is we have
a prediction about what time you're
going to wake up and then we're just
going to do it like setting the
thermostat we're going to just prepare
it for it to be ready at this time
then this is kind of
taking that
physical
biofeedback layer to another level but
also
what should we epistemically forage for
in the morning how do we
experience
that sleep-wake
transition in a way where like we wake
up and sort of like
sharpen or
become more vigilant
and focus on the things that matter and
that have impact and at the end of the
day sort of
have some unwind or some sort of
relaxing process so that we can move
into a healthy sleep
there was um
ah there was this
i'm watching a lot of youtube lately
it's like um
there's this one dude who tried to
replicate
a billionaire morning right
it was it was striking what the
billionaire does in the morning and
which is basically like
i'm doing all this to make my body
feel better and all that great and then
he did this stuff to think about who he
wanted to be today and what kind of
qualities he wanted to embody and it's
like
yo
i gotta think about not missing my bus
or whether i'm gonna freeze my house
outside or whether you know i might get
fired if i get laid like you see what i
mean like my concerns my direct
epistemic concerns in the morning are
fastly different from what that dude has
to care about because everything that
i'm talking about he's certain about
like he has no qualm about it he does
not care like
so
how might one sort of shift this well i
feel like there could be structures that
we could put in place in order for
someone to not feel like they have to
you know feel that but also
maybe a focus
i know it seems hard to say but maybe a
focus on the things that he has to focus
on
would potentially limit the sort of
you know
constant need to feel like you need to
put out fires
so let's say that i'm a smart interface
and i'm like well
this person needs to be certain about
these things because their life has x
constraints well maybe we're going to do
is give you x report and look you don't
need to worry about it it's there you
have that information now what about you
tried to think about things that are
longer scale what about you tried to
think about
things that if you had nothing else to
care about you'd start thinking about so
you know maybe these are the sort of
epistemic foraging that
would lead people to a slightly more
peaceful life but maybe i'm coming from
a very privileged place and maybe this
is completely unrealistic so you'd have
to ask people who
are much less privileged might have a
different view on this on this question
awesome
points
um
just in our last few minutes like
what are you going to continue to work
on or what are you excited about or what
do you want to talk about or ask
anything you want to talk about
well i mean you did you mentioned your
paper but we never got to it
we have time or
sure
so with um a handful of co-authors
we wrote a paper about um
using active imprints to study
specifically the epistemic community of
science and so we as a group read and
shared
your paper on epistemic communities and
then took the idea of like this
epistemic entity and now we've seen
active inference entities be at
different scales
that's
several years and many like um
different things we've talked about
there
including the narrative scale
and so we thought well
how could we model the scientific
epistemic ecosystem
how can we do
a systems description
of the scientific ecosystem so like the
entities
like the person but also the lab the
university the dao in the case of
decentralized science or like web 3 or
open science
how do we model the active entities
and
for the active entities
eventually flesh out a cognitive model
like
you've presented today
but also include
the informational entities which map not
on to the adaptive active inference
agents but the
mere active inference agents so we can
still model
the paper as like an entity but it
doesn't have any policy selection that
it can engage in
where or like a code can engage in
limited policy selection um when it's
used by computer system and so the goal
was to
develop
an ontology the eos the active entity
ontology for science
that would be able to
link up natural language descriptions
like i
sent a message to my friend
person friend sent a message so have the
natural language representation with the
graphical flowchart representation kind
of like a social network
of different kinds of entities including
the informational ones and then be able
to connect that to a simulation
architecture
so sorry you cut off what i think oh so
okay so
you were going to try and simulate
agents using your ontology so basically
like
so the first eos paper from last week
we focused a little bit more on the
conceptual and the history of
decentralized sense making
and history of science
and an introduction to web 3 and dsi
decentralized science
and then
some of our ongoing
work and collaborations are to
go from the
flow charts that we kind of sketched out
in some of the figures like a funding
motif or an information sharing motif or
communications motif
into
a simulation
that uses the active inference entity
model
okay wow you really need to talk to
maxwell about this like he's been trying
to think about how
communities
react to active inference specifically
and this this makes me feel this makes
me think of lactose right like how
there's this like core and then people
test out the the external hypotheses
until they reach the core or if they
don't reach the core then expands and so
there's something really cool there i
can't wait to
see more of this work
awesome um yeah i hope that we can
continue
strangely attracting and intertwining
and including
just collaborators from different
backgrounds in the discussion as
some people who are listening might be
hearing about active inference for the
first time
and
might be connecting with like a
community in us
that likes to do this kind of modeling
and framing and also there's people who
might be more familiar with the active
inference modeling and hopefully this
like brought their attention to a really
important
and contemporary
case and of course excellent recent
research
yes let's do a
interdisciplinary research for the win
cool
anything else you want to add
oh no we've covered a lot of graphs i
know i know seriously the time goes fast
so thanks a ton for joining see you
around
bye